בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today we do the, we are at the
last דף daf of מעילה, Meilah, דף כ"א. daf chaf-alef. Actually, technically
there is a little bit of כ"ב. chaf-bet. We start at the
top of the משנה. Mishnah. We are still dealing with the act
of מעילה. Meilah. I did want to make two comments of something
that I touched into yesterday, which is two things. First of all,
and this is going to be relevant for today, we've been talking
about how you do this act of stealing, and then we talked
about taking the beam and to what degree is it considered stealing
or
whatever. The ראב"ד Ravad says the point that I said, which is,
it is not this idea that you have to give it to
somebody else is not limited to
גזבר, gizbar, it really applies to anybody who has a right to
be having it in their home. So if you sanctify it, as
long as you're moving it from one place to another, that is
not stealing. Stealing in that case would only be if you gave
it to somebody else. Of course he says pretty
explicitly, or used, right, but we're talking about the stealing aspect. Of
course he says the obvious point that if you go ahead and
you go into the temple
warehouse or whatever and take it out from there and take it
home, that is obviously, you don't need to give it to somebody
else. So that is important that he expanded beyond literally the גזבר,
gizbar, and we will see some cases we are about to read
don't sound like they're talking about the גזבר, gizbar, but sound that
they have that same principle that just taking it is not considered
stealing until you give it to somebody else. I should say, by
the way, that when it comes to other things that you have
a right to have in your house, like if you have an
object in your house for safekeeping, a פיקדון, pikadon, what is the
word for פיקדון? pikadon?
Anyway, whatever it is. What's it called when somebody gives you something
for guarding and protecting and safekeeping? Anyway, if you have that in
your house, you're watching something for somebody, there's a principle of שליחות
יד, shlichus yad, which is really just moving it with the intent
to steal it. So here, though, that is not enough. Here it
has to be some type of an obvious act of taking. But
it is not limited to this problem as the ראב"ד Ravad says
again, it was not just גזבר, gizbar, anybody that has a right
for it to be in their home, then you would have to
give it out to somebody else to be considered an act of
stealing.
So the גזבר gizbar takes it and then he deposits it for
you for safekeeping. The moment you are שליחות יד shlichus yad in
it then...
Exactly, and that is שליחות יד, shlichus yad, but give it out
to somebody else.
No, the moment you...
No, you have a right for it to be in your house.
Then the גזבר gizbar puts it in your house and then the
moment you are שליחות יד shlichus yad on it then...
No, no, the principle of שליחות יד shlichus yad isn't relevant. For
there, if you have a right to be accessing it, you have
to take it out of your control and give it to somebody
else. The other point that I just wanted to make because we
mentioned it about two days ago, and it was a תוספתא, Tosefta,
but then I found, and we're going to start our משנה, Mishnah,
but then I saw that the רמב"ם Rambam rules like the תוספתא.
Tosefta. And that is that this whole idea that something stops being
קודש, kodesh, again, I make this point because conceptually it is very
powerful for me, this idea that after the act of מעילה Meilah
it stops, it loses its קדושה, kedusha, and we said of course
that that doesn't apply to קדושת הגוף, kedushas haguf, it is only
קדושת דמים, kedushas damim, קדושת בדק הבית, kedushas bedek habayis, and so
on. The רמב"ם Rambam says based on the תוספתא, Tosefta, even when
it is קדושת בדק הבית kedushas bedek habayis and קדושת דמים, kedushas
damim, that it loses its קדושה kedusha after מעילה, Meilah, that is
only the מעילה Meilah of stealing, that is not the מעילה Meilah
of benefiting. So if you
just warmed yourself with this wool that was belong to הקדש, hekdesh,
that is not, it doesn't lose its קדושה, kedusha, and there is
מעילה. Meilah. It loses its קדושה kedusha when you steal it, you
take it, and you give it to somebody else. And that, of
course, makes an enormous amount of sense, because since the whole קדושה
kedusha anyway by בדק הבית bedek habayis is about ownership, and therefore
the idea of taking away and giving to somebody else is the
most profound thing that would actually make it say that you removed
it from הקדש hekdesh and the קדושה kedusha goes away. Just deriving
benefit, although not allowed, would not have the power to remove the
קדושה. kedusha. So although it didn't sound that way from the משנה,
Mishnah, the רמב"ם Rambam reads it into the משנה Mishnah based on
the תוספתא. Tosefta. The ראב"ד Ravad doesn't like it. The ראב"ד Ravad
says he got this from the תוספתא, Tosefta, but it is not
what the הלכה halacha is. But anyway, but conceptually I find that
very interesting, and we had mentioned it before, so I wanted to
say that the רמב"ם Rambam rules that way.
Yeah, or you change it. Let's say you paint the wall.
So changing it, by building it into your house and so on,
that could be a type of an act of
stealing. That's true. שינוי קונה? shinui koneh? I understand, it's like what
the גמרא Gemara discussed about building the beam into your house. There
that could be an act of stealing, the act of transforming it,
yes.
And would it, because then we had a little
bit of a complication of whether you need to have half a
פרוטה perutah of פגם pagam and half a...
No, that you certainly can do, that is the משנה. Mishnah. But
the idea that you need a full פרוטה perutah of פגם pagam
plus a full פרוטה perutah of הנאה, hanaah, he sounds like that.
Although again, in other places it doesn't sound like that so much,
so I think the jury is still out on that. Let's start
now at...
שליחות יד, shlichus yad, is that somebody taking care of something?
No, no, that is to be a שומר, shomer, to be a
guard, a protector of an object in your safekeeping. שליחות יד shlichus
yad is when you take it for
yourself. So there, actually, פיקדון pikadon is the thing you're watching. Let's
take a look now at the משנה, Mishnah, top of כ"א עמוד
א'. chaf-alef amud alef. אמר לו. amar lo. So now we are,
this משנה Mishnah as we know, since the whole פרק perek is
called השליח שעשה, Hashliach sheasah, is about the idea that
this. It's not a שליחות shlichus I tell you Michael, go over
there and
there's some steaks over there and go eat one for me or
I don't even know how you would say it anyway, that would
not be an act of that would not be my act of
מעילה. me'ila. You are benefit. Okay, here the idea where I could
tell you something and it becomes my act of מעילה, me'ila,
it is when I tell you to take it and to give
it, it's about stealing. So it's not like you are directly the
one Michael, if I tell him like the case we had the
other day, I tell him to go give the meat to the
guests, he's not the one deriving benefit. The primary act of מעילה
me'ila is not benefit, the primary act of מעילה me'ila is it
was taken away from הקדש. Hekdesh. And there, since he's doing it
on my behalf, it's like I am the one taking it away
from הקדש. Hekdesh.
Okay, and that type of somebody could say I would have invited
this guest later on today, now that you invited him I don't
need
to. And then
I invite David
for dinner, you invited him for lunch, he says go give him
that steak and David comes to my house and it's like now
I don't need to eat because I already ate by you.
Okay, that's too complicated, I don't want to deal with that right
now. Okay, let's look at the משנה. mishna. אמר לו, Amar lo,
הבי לי מן החלון או מן הדלוסקמא. havei li min hachalon o
min hadluskema. So now here we're going to deal with when again
has the שליח shaliach done what I've said or not with this
idea that there is שליחות shlichus by מעילה me'ila and as long
as it's this type of an act of מעילה me'ila which is
about sort of stealing. So what's a דלוסקמא? dluskema? I'm going to
say. So you say to your שליח, shaliach, go bring to me,
go bring me some of those steaks or who knows what, oil,
money maybe, from the window or from the דלוסקמא dluskema which is
a box, והביא לו, veheivi lo, and he goes and he does
what you said. אף על פי שאמר בעל הבית לא היה בלבי
אלא מזה והביא מזה. Af al pi she'amar ba'al habayis lo haya
belibi ela mizeh veheivi mizeh. Now let's say there was more than
one window and stuff in more than one window or more than
one box and I said I didn't mean that box I meant
the other box, I didn't mean that window I meant the other
window. Nevertheless,
והביא מזה בעל הבית מעל. veheivi mizeh ba'al habayis maal. It's still
מעילה me'ila because although you might genuinely have been thinking that, the
principle is דברים שבלב אינם דברים. devarim shebelev einam devarim. What you're
thinking is not relevant, it's what you said. And since the שליח
shaliach did what you said, even if it might not have been
what you were thinking, it is considered to be that he was
acting on your behalf and therefore it is your action. Now what
it doesn't say of course is that okay, but he just brought
it to you, where's the act of מעילה? me'ila? It's just moving
something from one place to another, where's the act of מעילה? me'ila?
Now the easiest thing I would point to say is
you're not the גזבר, gizbar, you have no right to be handling
that stuff and therefore the act of מעילה me'ila is the actual
taking. The only idea that you have to give it out to
somebody else is when you have a right to be handling it.
If you're the גזבר gizbar and so on. If you're not the
גזבר gizbar and that's הקדש's Hekdesh money the very act of taking
can be מעילה. me'ila.
Not if you don't have a right to it, okay? If it's
something that you don't have a right to have in your house
and a right to be handled, then therefore that should be the
case where the taking actually is an act of מעילה. me'ila. Although
again, even though the גמרא Gemara made that clear that just the
moving is only not מעילה me'ila by a גזבר, gizbar, there's a
hesitation in general to explain מעילה me'ila just by moving it from
one place to the other, even though you could say it's not
a גזבר gizbar that's the מעילה. me'ila. So it could be wait
a minute it's so right I don't know I got there, who
knows but I mean I guess that's the point Michael's making. If
it's in a window and it's your window but maybe it's not
your window maybe it's הקדש's Hekdesh window or something, but again because
of that because the scenario somehow sounds like you do have a
right to be handling it, so then the מעילה me'ila is not
just the taking of it. And then תוספות Tosafos says ultimately then
the מעילה me'ila is that after he takes it and gives it
to you, you go ahead and give it to somebody else. I
know. So that's why it's a little funny, it's avoiding that point.
I would rather understand it that you're not the גזבר, gizbar, you
don't have a right to be handling it and that's the מעילה.
me'ila. Maybe someone else as well. Maybe. Okay, now we go on.
רישא גופא. Reisha gof. אבל אם אמר לו, Aval im amar lo,
הבי לי מן החלון והביא לי מן הדלוסקמא, havei li min hachalon
veheivi li min hadluskema, he says bring for me from the window
and he brings from the box, או מן הדלוסקמא והביא לו מן
החלון, o min hadluskema veheivi lo min hachalon, or bring for me
from the box and instead he brings from the window, then השליח
מעל. hashaliach maal. Then the שליח shaliach is the one that is
מועל mo'el because he did not do what you said. Even if
it's more or less similar type of a thing as long as
he takes it from the place that wasn't the place I said,
it's his act not my act. And again the question is where
was ultimately the moving out of רשות? reshus? Is it then I
gave it to someone then I'm considered his שליח? shaliach? He gave
it to me, he was acting on his own, then I gave
it to someone. So now it's effectively I'm doing it for it's
a little all this is unclear where was the final act of
מעילה. me'ila. The easiest thing like I said to say is that
this is actually a case where the taking itself is the act
of מעילה. me'ila. Now we go on. That's case number one. השליח
Hashaliach now we get to something even more interesting.
שלח ביד חרש שוטה וקטן. shelach beyad cheresh shoteh vekatan.
You sent it through a minor, a deaf-mute, or somebody who is
not of sane mind. And these people normally are not considered בר
דעת, bar da'as, are not considered people
of that have a. I'm trying to think of the English term.
I literally, I know it means this, but there's a legal term
for this, somebody that's considered a an adult and an age of
majority and somebody that's an agent within, you know, within law, so
they cannot be considered and therefore, somebody
who's mentally competent.
Well, no, but not just mental competence, it's also an age of
majority if somebody is too small, a minor. Anyway, but you know,
so somebody that's really like a legal agent, like a legal, anyway.
So these types of cases normally there would not be a concept
of agency, of שליחות. shlichus. If I made this person a שליח
shaliach to take תרומה terumah for me or to give a גט
get to my wife or to give קידושין kiddushin to a woman,
it would not be valid. There's no שליחות. shlichus. But here it's
going to say there is שליחות. shlichus. שלח ביד חרש שוטה וקטן,
Shalach be-yad cheresh shoteh ve-katan, אם עשו שליחותו, im asu shlichuto,
if they did what I sent them to do, בעל הבית baal
habayit מעל, moal, it's my מעילה. meilah. Wow, they did my on
my behalf. לא עשו שליחותו Lo asu shlichuto if they didn't, חנוני
chenvani מעל. moal.
So then it is, now where did the חנוני chenvani come? So
so here we're going to say is I told them right, take
this money and maybe this is now the scenario at the top
as well, but take this money and go buy some cheese for
me at the market, okay? So they took the money, they bought
the cheese. Now, if they're doing what I said, then the giving
to the חנוני, chenvani, the giving to the storekeeper is the act
of מעילה, meilah, they're taking it out of my control, giving it
out. That's the מעילה. meilah. Who did it? If they're doing what
I said, then I did it. If they're not, if they are
not doing what I said, they bought cheese, they bought a milk.
Okay, they didn't do what I said. So I didn't do it
and normally you would say they did it. If the, if they
were a, if they were not, if if it was an adult
of sound mind, it would be his מעילה. meilah. But because this
is a חרש שוטה וקטן, cheresh shoteh ve-katan, you can't attribute an
act of, a responsible act to them. So where, if I'm not
doing it, it's they're also not seen as the מועל. moel. And
who's the מועל? moel? The חנוני chenvani when he takes the money.
Okay? Now again, you could say, oh, it's not his fault. It's
for sure not his fault, but מעילה meilah is בשוגג. be-shogeg. So
how do you know this versus a שוגג?
shogeg? What?
Well, that's the question. Does אונס ones really matter here? I mentioned
the other day that, you know, אונס ones might be different, but
it might not actually be true. Okay? So let's take a look.
שלח ביד פיקח. Shalach be-yad pikeach.
Now let's say I sent through a person who is like an
adult of sound mind to go buy milk for me or cheese.
ונזכר עד שלא הגיע אצל חנוני. Ve-nizkar ad shelo higia eitzel chenvani.
Now, of course we already talked about the case that he, if
he did what I said, I'm מועל, moel, if he didn't do
what I said, he's מועל. moel. Now, but let's say it's not
a case of following or not following. Let's say it's the case
of he's on the way and I remember, oh my god, that
was הקדש hekdesh money.
Oh true, you sent a שליח. shaliach.
I sent the שליח shaliach and then I remembered, oh my god,
I just sent him with הקדש hekdesh money. Now, why, why would
that be a difference? Because the whole idea of מעילה meilah is
בשוגג. be-shogeg. And here, in a way, it's still בשוגג, be-shogeg, it's
out of my control, the guy's already there, I'm not trying to
sin, but, but apparently what we learned from this משנה mishnah is
that when I'm aware that it's הקדש hekdesh money that's being misused,
that's not מעילה. meilah. Now, maybe it's, now
certainly not מעילה meilah for the question about, you know, that's interesting
questions here. Can be a מזיד meizid in מעילה meilah and there's
even a גמרא gemara that discusses what's the punishment for מזיד? meizid?
מיתה בידי שמים mitah biyedei shamayim and so on. But it's not
the מעילה meilah for the sense of let's say having to bring
a קרבן, korban, having to pay a חומש chomesh for the idea
that the money goes out לחולין. lechullin. Because here you realize only
one person is going to be מועל, moel, right? Because as soon
as one person is מועל moel the money goes out לחולין. lechullin.
It's your classic case of בדק הבית, bedek habayit, it's a case
of stealing what the רמב״ם rambam says is what works by בדק
הבית. bedek habayit. Okay, so therefore as long as, if I remember
then I can't be מועל. moel. I can't be the one that's
מועל moel and therefore it's not going to go out לחולין lechullin
on my behalf. It can't be attributed to me. Now you would
say okay, then the, maybe the שליח? shaliach? But the שליח shaliach
like an אונס. ones. So who's the guy that's going to be
מועל moel in this scenario? So let's take a look. 1 minute.
שלח ביד פיקח ונזכר עד שלא הגיע אצל חנוני, Shalach be-yad pikeach
ve-nizkar ad shelo higia eitzel chenvani, חנוני chenvani מעל moal לכשיוציא. le-ksheyotzi.
The חנוני chenvani is מועל moel when he actually spends the money.
Okay? Why? Because basically for some reason the שליח shaliach isn't מועל
moel either. Because the שליח shaliach did what I said, so we're
assuming although the גמרא gemara will, will modify it, we're assuming that
the שליח shaliach is like me. If I'm not מועל, moel, the
שליח shaliach isn't מועל. moel. Okay? So therefore it's the חנוני chenvani
who is מועל. moel. Now here interestingly you could have said that
the חנוני chenvani is מועל moel when he takes the money, right?
Because he, the money is הקדש hekdesh and he's taking it. But
again you get this idea that we're very loath to say that
the act of taking is in itself an act of מעילה. meilah.
So loath, right, like loath to say that the act of taking
is in itself an act of מעילה. meilah. So even here where
the חנוני chenvani is a third party, since he's actually being given
the money, okay, the taking of the money is not מעילה, meilah,
מעילה meilah is only now when he uses it. If the בעל
הבית baal habayit or the שליח shaliach would have been מועל moel
it would have made it חולין. chullin. But since they're seen here
presumably as one unit, שליח shaliach is doing what he was told
and the בעל הבית baal habayit isn't מועל moel so the שליח
shaliach isn't, the גמרא's gemara going to change that. Therefore the חנוני
chenvani takes the money into his possession with permission and it's only
when he spends... uses the money is that considered the act of
מעילה. Me'ilah. Okay. כיצד יעשה? Keitzad Ya'aseh? Now what should the בעל
הבית Ba'al haBayis do if he realizes this and he wants to
get the חנווני Chanvani out of מעילה? Me'ilah? Okay what's he going
to do?
What's the חנווני? Chanvani?
Oh a storekeeper? Oh, sorry, the storekeeper. So נוטל פרוטה או כלי,
notel prutah o klee, so he takes a you know a פרוטה,
prutah, a nickel or some type of a thing, a pen ואומר,
v'omer, and this is what you should say, you're the one that
sent this guy with the money and you now realize it's הקדש,
Hekdesh, you can fix it. Here's what
you say: פרוטה של הקדש בכל מקום שהוא, Prutah shel Hekdesh b'chol
makom shehu, that dollar of הקדש Hekdesh or nickel or whatever it
is, wherever it is, and whoever has it if the my שליח
Shliach has it, if the storekeeper has it, wherever that הקדש Hekdesh
money is, you מחולל על זה, mechulal al zeh, I'm transferring the
קדושה Kedushah to this, to my nickel or to this vessel or
whatever I have, and therefore the קדושה Kedushah goes off of that
item. This I'll give to the בית המקדש Beis haMikdash and therefore
when he spends it, he's not spending any הקדש's Hekdesh money שהקדש
נפדה בכסף ובשוה כסף. she'Hekdesh nifdeh b'kesef u'v'shaveh kesef. You can redeem
money with either with other money or you know קדושה Kedushah with
either money or with something that is of value. Now of course
the interesting thing here is you know
but it's not under your control. It's in the חנווני's Chanvani control.
On the other hand, it doesn't belong to the חנווני. Chanvani. It
belongs to הקדש. Hekdesh. So it doesn't really matter that it's in
the חנווני's Chanvani control. You can redeem הקדש. Hekdesh. It gets to
other questions though that if I sanctify my car for בדק הבית,
Bedek haBayis, who can redeem it? Can I can you redeem it?
So actually if you might remember we actually learned גמרות Gemaras that
actually sound seem to say that even a third party can redeem
it. Anyway, maybe I am the first maybe I'm not a third
party, maybe I'm the guy that sanctified the money and I for-
that's what it was doing in my house and I forgot that
I sanctified it okay and that's why I sent my guy to
go buy the milk. So even if the storekeeper's holding it, it's
still money I sanctified and I still now can transfer the קדושה
Kedushah away. So that's how I can solve the problem if I
realize in the middle. Yes.
It's going to work for קדושת דמים Kedushas damim it's never going
to work for קדושת הגוף. Kedushas haguf.
Well, that is true but all of this is about קדושת דמים
Kedushas damim because all of this is assuming that it's being s-
that we're dealing right that it's going out to חולין Chullin the
first time it's being מעילה Me'ilah and so on. But that's true,
it's all assuming that, yeah. If it's a קרבן Korban without whatever
then you're really stuck. Okay so
now let's take a look
again,
this idea of the storekeeper being held responsible even though he might
do the exact same act and in one case it's מעילה Me'ilah
and in one case it's not, depending like he might give the
agent sugar. Right. And in one case, in other words he it
has it's like several stages removed from the connection in my mind
because the sugar might be the correct thing or it might not
be the correct thing and he has no idea about it.
Well you mean whether the שליח Shliach is doing שליחותו shlichuso or
not doing.
In other words the שליח Shliach was sent to get sugar, okay?
So if he gives him sugar then he's that's fine. But if
he gives him milk, then
that's the שליח's Shliach מעילה. Me'ilah. The only case where it's not
the שליח's Shliach מעילה Me'ilah and he has to worry about it.
No, if the שליח Shliach does the wrong thing then it's the
שליח's Shliach מעילה. Me'ilah.
No, but if he's
incompetent so then it's like this guy this guy has no idea
what's coming to him.
It's true. That's true. But again, you know, so you could say
it's dangerous to be a storekeeper. But so maybe don't do business
with חרש שוטה וקטן, Cheresh Shoteh v'Katan, you know, they'll have a
חרש שוטה וקטן Cheresh Shoteh v'Katan disability act. So the point is
is that is that presumably these scenarios here are very unlikely. But
you're right, there could be a case where the בעל הבית Ba'al
haBayis is total where the storekeeper's totally innocent and winds up he's
doing מעילה Me'ilah and how is he supposed to know? Absolutely. So
we'll talk about I'll mention that in a minute because the מפרש
Mefaresh here gives a gives a what do you sort of quotes
a גמרא Gemara about that. Let's take a look at the גמרא
Gemara on this. The גמרא Gemara first says מאי קא משמע לן?
Mai ka mashma lan? What's the first thing teaching me? That oh
I wasn't thinking about this I was thinking about that. It seems
to me דברים שבלב אינם דברים. Devarim she'be'lev einam devarim. What you're
thinking doesn't matter, it's all about what you said. Okay, pretty important
principle להלכה. l'Halachah. Okay, so now it says like this,
hold on I just want to see something. Okay now. ושלח ביד
חרש שוטה וקטן אם עשו שליחותם. V'shalach b'yad Cheresh Shoteh v'Katan im
asu shlichusam. So now the amazing חידוש chiddush that even this incompetent
person חרש שוטה וקטן, Cheresh Shoteh v'Katan, they are considered a שליח
shliach and it's my מעילה. Me'ilah. So the גמרא Gemara asks the
question we all ask we all want to ask והלא לאו בני
שליחות נינהו? v'ha lav b'nei shlichus ninhu? These are people that don't
have agency. So אמר רבי אלעזר Amar Rabbi Elazar עשאם כמעטן של
זיתים. asam k'ma'atan shel zeisim. They made them like a barrel of
like a vat of olives. What does that mean? תנן: Tnan: הזיתים
אימתי מקבלין טומאה? ha'zeisim eimasai mikablin tumah? When do olives become are
susceptible for טומאה, Tumah, right? When a liquid goes on them after
they're picked and when you want the liquid to go on them.
So the הלכה Halachah is משיזיעו, mi'she'yaziyu, זו היא מעטנן zeh tam'atan
when they sweat, which means a little of the liquid is coming
out of it. The sweating that they do in the vat בלא
זיעת הקופה belo ze'as ha'kupah not in the basket when you're picking
them and putting them directly in the basket you don't want the
liquid to come out yet you lose the liquid. When you however
put them in the vat, then you want
the liquid or you're okay.
So the liquid that comes out causes them to be מקבל טומאה.
mekabbel tuma. Why is it all relevant? So תוספות Tosafos says it's
a very bizarre analogy, תוספות Tosafos points out, but the point basically
is you don't always need to do something directly. Sometimes something is
done according to your will and that's good enough as if you
did. So the fact that
here, when they're in the basket you don't want it, when they're
in the vat you do want it, so the fact that they
are getting wet according to your will even though nobody is actually
doing it, that counts. Now of course that's a very bad analogy
because here we never had a thought that an action was required.
The whole הלכה halakha from the very beginning is they were wet
and it was something that you wanted. There was not even a
concept of an action. So תוספות Tosafos really points it out and
doesn't like it. Let's read the next example. Next example is better.
רבי יוחנן אמר, Rabbi Yochanan amar, כההוא דתנינא, ka-hahu de-tanina, like we
taught over in עירובין, Eruvin, נתנו על גבי הקוף והוליכו, או על
גבי הפיל והוליכו. nasnu al gabei ha-kof ve-holicho, o al gabei ha-pil
ve-holicho. You put your עירוב, eiruv, this is the עירוב eiruv about
that when you put something outside the city limit, then it allows
you to walk from that object beyond. So you put it on
a monkey and the monkey brought it to the place, a trained
monkey. Or on an elephant and it brought it to the place
where you wanted it. We'll skip the parentheses, I'll go back and
talk about it in a second. הרי זה עירוב, harei zeh eiruv,
that counts. Now that's a good example. You didn't do it yourself.
אלמא, alma, you see, כעביד שליחותיה, ka-avid shelichuteih, sometimes you don't need
to personally be doing the act, you just
need it to be done through your efforts, even though it's not
being done through a concept of agency or directly by you. So
הכא נמי, hacha nami, עביד שליחותיה, avid shelichuteih, here too we say
your agency has been done. One minute now, the problem is that
תוספות Tosafos says that there's another גמרא Gemara that the גמרא Gemara
over in עירובין Eruvin actually says that if they do this, it
doesn't work. It doesn't work. And תוספות Tosafos first says well maybe
the difference is is that it works if somebody takes it off
of the donkey, off of the elephant and puts it down for
you. And that's the parenthesis. The parenthesis says ואמר לאחר לקבלו ממנו,
ve-amar le-acher lekabbelo mimmenu, somebody else took it. Of course תוספות Tosafos
said but if that were true then your whole proof goes away
because then in the end the reason it works is because somebody
put it down on your behalf. So תוספות Tosafos says we'll have
to say the difference is is that in one case it just
fell off
like, one case it went off where it went off. The other
case you were observing it and it fell off and therefore that
putting or it was put down and therefore that's as if you
did it. So anyway that's a little tricky. Not everything is considered
to be as if you did it. You need to somehow be
involved in it. But the point is if you're involved at a
certain level even if without technical שליחות shelichus it works, which by
the way points out to makes the fence here by the fence
of מעילה. me'ila. Because normally אין שליח לדבר עבירה, ein shaliach li-dvar
aveirah, why should it? Your sin not my sin. But here the
idea is the way we conceptualize the מעילה, me'ila, it's more about
the act, not about the act but about the effect of having
it removed or removing it from הקדש. hekdesh. So if that was
done through my initiative and people acting on my behalf, ultimately I'm
the one that got this away from הקדש. hekdesh. Okay, the same
way for example, we said another example which is if I take
some oil and I put it on you, even though you're the
one benefiting, I am the one that caused that benefit to happen.
So the causal idea here of having it removed, having it misdirected
is the focus and therefore even if there's not a concept of
שליחות shelichus as long as they're doing what I said, that is
considered an extension of me. Charlie you had a question?
Is this a source for the often heard statement that a monkey
could do it?
Well, yes, actually that probably is where that was coming from is
that the גמרא Gemara sometimes uses a monkey as a way of
speaking about that it doesn't require, but of course it's still offensive
because it still says it doesn't require a בר דעת. bar da'as.
So yes, but I think it's even in a good proof if
ואמר לאחר לקבלו ממנו ve-amar le-acher lekabbelo mimmenu because that's our example
here.
הנחתמי הוא אחר, ha-nachestami hu acher, I am sending it to a
חרש שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh ve-katan basically and
basically then the חנוני chanvani would be מועל, mo'el, not me. And
we say that if they did what I said I'm מועל. mo'el.
Right, no, but just like it's a good עירוב eiruv if I
have somebody else at the other end take it off, it's during
my מעילה me'ila but I have somebody else...
no, no, because then it's the act of the other person which
is what's significant. And if that were true here, that the only
significance were the act of the חנוני, chanvani, then the חנוני chanvani
would be the מועל, mo'el, not me through my שליח. shaliach. Okay,
let's keep on going. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, שב
ואפיקיה. shav ve-afikeih. So now this is the case about remembering. You
remembered so then that gets you and the שליח shaliach off the
hook, it becomes the חנוני's chanvani thing if he spends it, not
just takes it, and then the way you get out is you
redeem it. So the גמרא Gemara says ואף גב דלא אידכר שליח,
ve-af gav de-lo idkar shaliach, what my remembering is enough to get
it out of מעילה me'ila even without the שליח? shaliach? ורמינהי, u-reminhi,
I'll ask you about that. נזכר בעל הבית, nizkar ba'al ha-bayis, we
have a ברייתא braisa that says if the בעל הבית ba'al ha-bayis
remembers ולא נזכר שליח, velo nizkar shaliach, מעל, ma'al, that if I
remember and the שליח shaliach does not remember, then Excuse me, השליח
מהו. hashaliach mahu. So I remembered, it gets me out of the
equation, but he doesn't, so he's still now the one that's unwittingly
being מוציא motzi the money, taking the money out, he's the מועל.
mo'el. We don't just make him an extension of me, once I'm
out of the equation, even again, we might thought that he is
an extension because he's still acting on my behest, but this ברייתא
beraita teaches us no, it says once I'm out of the equation,
he's the מועל, mo'el, not me.
Even if he had no idea?
Even if he had no idea. So how do you explain the
משנה? mishnah? So and this is true at least the- at least
the question about the text חנווני, chanvani, only when we both remember
do we both get out of the picture and then it's the
חנווני. chanvani. So אמר רב ששת Amar Rav Sheshet מתניתין כשנזכרו שניהם.
matnitin keshenizkeru sheneihem. You're right, not only you remembered, but the שליח
shaliach remembered as well. Of course, if the שליח shaliach remembered, why
is he going and spending the money? But you know, who knows,
maybe he thinks, look, this is הקדש's hekdesh money, but you know,
my master said it, maybe it's a case of a servant, you
know, I gotta do what he says, even though this is הקדש's
hekdesh money. But he does- he is aware of it, and nevertheless,
he's still going ahead and spending it. Okay, and nevertheless, it's not
me, it's the- it's the שליח, shaliach,
and therefore it's the חנווני. chanvani. But if I don't remember, if
I remember and the שליח shaliach doesn't, then it's the שליח's shaliach
מעילה. meilah. Now, the מפרש mefaresh here points out the problem that
in all of these scenarios it's like, you know, what do you
expect of the guy? Like in the first scenario, like, what do
you expect of the חנווני? chanvani? Like, he didn't know. Of course,
if the שליח shaliach remembered, he should have told him, but he
didn't. Okay, or, you know, if I remembered it's the שליח's shaliach
מעילה, meilah, what how can we make the שליח shaliach liable here
by this real case of אונס? ones? So if you take a
look at the מפרש mefaresh here, he says the following, he says
one two three four five lines down
in the middle-sized lines, he says like this: והיינו דאמרינן במסכת חגיגה
האי דמעל השליח היינו כהררים התלויין בשערה. vehaynu d'amrinan be'masechet chagigah hai
d'maal hashaliach haynu kehararim hateluyin b'sa'arah. Right,
there's a משנה mishnah in מסכת חגיגה masechet chagigah that says some
הלכות halachot are like mountains suspended by a hair. Okay, so it
says this הלכה halacha is one of them. Why? And look at
what he says: דשליח עניא דא מאי קעביד? deshaliach anya da mai
ka'avid? What did he do? הלא עביד שליחותא דבעל הבית, halo avid
shlichuta de'ba'al habayit, he's just listening to the בעל הבית, ba'al habayit,
and now you're telling him he's מועל mo'el because the בעל הבית
ba'al habayit remembered. So basically, yeah, it's a real problem, nobody here
is to fault, everybody is אונס ones except the בעל הבית, ba'al
habayit, but you can be אונס ones and still be a מועל,
mo'el, and that's what actually the גמרא Gemara says. Yeah, it's a
real problem, but that's the הלכה. halacha.
What is the אונס ones category?
אונס ones means, like, it's- it could mean compelled, but it could
also mean, like, complete, you know,
complete without fault, like, it's, you know, it's
blameless almost. Yeah.
But my question is,
when you say נזכר, nizkar, you have to have known to remember.
You know what I mean? Meaning, if you didn't know, I don't
see how it's- meaning it means that both the בעל הבית ba'al
habayit and the שליח shaliach knew at some point this was הקדש
hekdesh money. It's not like he's just doing, in which case then
if נזכר בעל הבית nizkar ba'al habayit and the שליח shaliach forgot
because he knew at some point it was הקדש, hekdesh, not that
he had no idea.
I understand what you're saying and I'm saying that no, that if
the- if it were possible that if you're saying that if the
שליח shaliach were totally unwitting, he had never any knowledge, then the
בעל הבית, ba'al habayit, then what are you saying? Then he would
be- it wouldn't be his fault.
In other words, if
what you want to suggest that if he was totally unwitting, never
had any knowledge, then
in this other cases we have
that what happened and then the בעל הבית ba'al habayit remembered, then
nobody would be to blame. Potentially. What? Potentially. And it would be
the חנווני chanvani at most. So why didn't the גמרא Gemara say
that that was the answer? That's why the משנה mishnah says that
it's the חנווני. chanvani. Why did it have to have give say
that it's a case that they both remembered? According to you, well,
which would be evidence that what you're saying is not correct. Okay,
let's take a look now at the next משנה. mishnah. נתן לו
פרוטה. natan lo p'rutah. אמר לו amar lo הבי לי בחציה נרות.
havi li be'chetzyah neirot. Here's going to be other examples of did
he listen to the בעל הבית ba'al habayit or not. So he
gave him a dollar, פרוטה, p'rutah, actually a פרוטה p'rutah is more
like a nickel but we'll call it a dollar. He gave him
a dollar and he said to him, bring me with half of
this some נרות. neirot. It doesn't literally mean wax candles, that's not
what they primarily had, they primarily had oil lamps. So there are
the מפרש mefaresh here says it means yeah, it means like oil
lamps, things in which you put the oil, little, you know, little,
you know, if you ever go to those archeological, those museums you
see all those tiny little like oil lamps. So go bring me
some of those with half of this money. ובחציה פתילות, u've'chetzyah psilot,
and with the other half of the פרוטה p'rutah go buy wicks.
והלך והביא לו בכולה פתילות, vehalach vehevi lo be'chulah psilot, he went
and he spent it all on wicks או בכולה נרות, o be'chulah
neirot, or all on those lamps. או שאמר לו o she'amar lo
הבי לי בכולה נרות havi li be'chulah neirot או בכולה פתילות. o
be'chulah psilot. He said spend it all on wicks or he said
spend it all on lamps והלך והביא לו בחציה נרות ובחציה פתילות,
vehalach vehevi lo be'chetzyah neirot u've'chetzyah psilot, he split it half and
half. שניהם לא מעלו. sheneihem lo ma'alu. They both didn't do מעילה.
meilah. Why? Because presumably he did follow the בעל הבית ba'al habayit
for the first half, right? The בעל הבית ba'al habayit said get
me half and half. So let's say, so he bought all. So
the first half פרוטה p'rutah he was listening to
the בעל הבית. ba'al habayit. Ah, but there's no מעילה meilah with
a half פרוטה. p'rutah. The second half פרוטה p'rutah he was doing
his own thing, there's no מעילה meilah on his half פרוטה. p'rutah.
Okay, and the same is when the בעל הבית ba'al habayit says
says all and he only buys half. So for half of it
he's listening to the בעל הבית ba'al habayit and the half that
he that he didn't listen that was his own but both Those
are only a half פרוטה. prutah. Okay, now, שניהם לא מעלו. sheneihem
lo ma'alu. אבל, aval, and then, and then now presumably by the
way you realize what it would mean is if it was the
same storeowner of the storeowner would be מועל mo'el when he would
be bought from. אבל אם אמר ליה, aval im amar lei, הביא
לי בחצי נרות ממקום פלוני. havei li b'chezi neiros mimakom peloni. He
says go spend half a פרוטה prutah to buy lamps from that
place, from
Joe's. ובחצי פתילות ממקום פלוני, u'vchezi psilos mimakom peloni, and spend the
half and go get the wicks from Frank's. והלך והביא לו נרות
ממקום פתילות ופתילות ממקום נרות, v'halach v'heivi lo neiros mimakom psilos u'psilos
mimakom neiros, and he reversed it, which he bought in which store.
So even though it's all the same, we've learned before any slight
deviation you're not a שליח. shaliach. So in that case, השליח מעל.
hashaliach ma'al. The שליח shaliach was מועל. mo'el. Because the שליח shaliach
misspent both half פרוטות. prutos. So both half פרוטות prutos were the
שליח's shaliach's on his own, and therefore was the שליח's shaliach's מעילה.
me'ilah. נתן לו שתי פרוטות. nasan lo shtei prutos. Now you gave
him two פרוטות. prutos. ואמר לו, v'amar lo, לך והביא לי אתרוג.
leich v'havei li esrog. Go buy me an אתרוג esrog for two
פרוטות. prutos. My god, if you could get an אתרוג esrog for
two פרוטות, prutos, okay, maybe it wasn't סוכות. Sukkos. Maybe it wasn't
סוכות. Sukkos. והלך והביא לו באחת אתרוג ובאחת רימון. v'halach v'heivi lo
b'achas esrog u'vachas rimon. And he came back with an אתרוג esrog
that he only spent one פרוטה prutah on and a pomegranate for
one פרוטה. prutah. Now, what's that case? שניהם מעלו. sheneihem ma'alu. They
were both מועל. mo'el. Why? Because buying you the אתרוג esrog for
a פרוטה prutah is considered to still be doing what you sold
him. Now you can challenge that and we're going to see in
a minute that רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda's going to challenge that. But
he did buy for you a פרוטה prutah with at least some
of the money you sent him. So number, so that he did.
So that's your מעילה. me'ilah. Then when he went ahead and bought
with the pomegranate with the other פרוטה, prutah, that was him acting
completely on his own, so that's his מעילה. me'ilah. רבי יהודה אומר,
Rabbi Yehuda omer, בעל הבית לא מעל. ba'al habayis lo ma'al. No,
in that case the owner did not do מועל mo'el even by
the אתרוג. esrog. Why? שהוא אומר לו, she'hu omer lo, אתרוג גדול
הייתי מבקש והבאת לי קטן ורע. esrog gadol hayisi mevakesh v'heiveisa li
katan v'ra. It's not like if you buy me an אתרוג esrog
for one פרוטה prutah you've done what I've asked. No, I wanted
a big אתרוג, esrog, a nice one. You bought me a tiny
icky one. So therefore that's completely not what I was asking for
and it's not half of what I was asking for, it's not
at all what I was asking for, and therefore I have not,
you have not done my agency at all. Similarly, נתן לו דינר
זהב. nasan lo diner zahav. You gave him a דינר. diner. ואמר
לו, v'amar lo, golden דינר, diner, and the golden מדינה. medinah. ואמר
לו, v'amar lo, לך והביא לי חלוק. leich v'havei li chaluk. Go
buy me a shirt. A nice, expensive shirt, right? Go buy me
a nice garment, it's an Armani חלוק. chaluk. והלך והביא לו בשלושה.
v'halach v'heivi lo bishlosha. And he went and he bought him a
shirt with only three סלעים slaim חלוק. chaluk. ובשלושה טלית. u'vishlosha tallis.
And with the other three סלעים, slaim, which is half of the
דינר, diner, he bought the shirt, the other half he bought like
a טלית. tallis. This doesn't mean a טלית tallis with ציצית, tzitzis,
it means like a, you know, an outer coat, a garment to
wrap in and stuff. שניהם מעלו. sheneihem ma'alu. They were both מועל.
mo'el. Why? Because I did what the בעל הבית ba'al habayis asked
for the first
half, I got him a cloak, so that's partly at least what
he asked for, and that's his מעילה. me'ilah. And the rest was
my own thing, that's my מעילה. me'ilah. And again, רבי יהודה אומר,
Rabbi Yehuda omer, Rabbi Yehuda says בעל הבית לא מעל. ba'al habayis
lo ma'al. No, I'm sorry, the בעל הבית ba'al habayis did not
מועל. mo'el. The שליח shaliach didn't do at all what he asked.
He didn't do half what he asked. שהוא אומר, she'hu omer, חלוק
גדול הייתי מבקש והבאת לי קטן ורע. chaluk gadol hayisi mevakesh v'heiveisa
li katan v'ra. I was, I wanted a
nicer Armani shirt. והבאת לי v'heiveisa li Kmart shirt. Excuse me, it's
not half of what I asked, it's not at all what I
asked. So it's not the בעל הבית's ba'al habayis's מעילה. me'ilah. Okay,
let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. שמע מינה. shema mina.
We can infer from
there, the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma that argues on רבי יהודה, Rabbi
Yehuda, right? 'Cause רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda's position obviously makes a certain
amount of intuitive
sense. So you hear from the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma that מאן
דאמר לשלוחו זיל זבין לי כורא דארעא. man d'amar lishlucho, zil zavin
li kura d'ara. Go buy me an acre of land. ואזל וזבן
ליה לתכא. v'azal v'zavan lei lischa. And he goes and buys you
a half acre. You remember a day or two ago we had
the reverse. I told him buy me a half acre, he buys
me an acre. Is he a שליח shaliach for me? If he
does more, does he remain being the שליח shaliach for the half
that he did, you know, for the part that was overlapped with
what I asked. For, so here, so that he did more than
I asked. Here he did less than I asked. I say buy
an acre, he buys a half acre. Is that still a binding
act? Is he still my agent for that purpose and do I
take possession of it or not? קנה לוקח. kani lokeiach. So there,
so from our משנה Mishna it sounds like you're still an agent
for that purpose and that I would purchase it under those circumstances.
Right? You got it? Because the משנה Mishna says that if I
go and tell him buy me an אתרוג esrog for two and
he buys me an אתרוג esrog for one, that the אתרוג esrog
is my מעילה. me'ilah. So even though he did half of what
I asked for, not the full, it still is, he still is
my שליח shaliach and it's my מעילה. me'ilah. So if he's my
שליח shaliach and it's my מעילה, me'ilah, then that means that in
an analogous case, if I just sent him to buy an acre
and he did half an acre, he's still my שליח shaliach and
the purchase is still binding.
But Rabbi Yochanan is not,
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda you mean. Right, we're dealing with the opinion
that argues on רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. Exactly. But this is the
opinion that argues on רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, so that would say
doing half you're still my agent. So the גמרא Gemara says not
necessarily. אמר, amar, you can say, הכא היכי דמי. hacha heichi dami.
What are we talking about? דאייתי ליה שוה שש בשלוש. de'aisei lei
shaveh sheish b'shalosh. He says we're talking about... That he bought something
worth six for three, that actually it was like a good, he
must
have came home with a bargain. So what do you say? So
I said go buy me for a דינר dinar a shirt. And
he says look, I got, this was normally worth a דינר, dinar,
but today it was half, it was on sale half price, so
I got it for you for only half. So there, of course
he did my שליחות, shlichus, he got me the full item that
I wanted. Okay? So therefore you cannot prove that if somebody does
half of what I said, it still works. Here he did all
of what I said, he just got it at half the price.
Of course the question is then why is רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
arguing, which is what the גמרא Gemara is going to say. Okay?
So גמרא Gemara says אימא סיפא, eima seifa, let's look at the
end. רבי יהודה אומר בעל הבית אומר לו יכול לומר לו חלוק
גדול הייתי מבקש והבאת לי חלוק קטן ורע. Rabbi Yehuda omer ba'al
ha-bayis omer lo yachol lomar lo chaluk gadol hayisi mevakesh ve-hevesa li
chaluk katan ve-ra.
So he says what is he... רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says, no
sorry, you didn't do at all what I asked. I wanted a
nice beautiful one, you got me a small ugly one. So I
don't... okay you got you...
then the answer is obvious and you say you know, if this
one was on
sale, exactly דאמר ליה, de-amar lei, because now I'll say to him,
I gave you a full דינר dinar to spend, you're telling me
there was a great sale going on? אי הות דינר כולה, Ei
havas dinar kula, if you would have spent the whole דינר, dinar,
הייתי שוה שני דינר, hayisi shavei shenei dinar, you could have got
me a shirt worth two דינר. dinar.
So therefore he... so but now we're saying like this because by
the way what this points to is the is that is that
the גמרא Gemara seems to be inclined to the to the position
of רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. There's a certain thing that's very persuasive
about רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda point. I don't care that you got
me a shirt, or you didn't get me what I asked, you
got me a half acre, I'm looking for a full acre. It's
not half of what I asked, it's not at all what I
asked. And the גמרא Gemara says, you know what, maybe in general
that's true and when a שליח shaliach does half, he's not doing
anything and this is a very special case where he did all
what you asked but at half price. And there the תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma says fine, he was your שליח shaliach and רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda says no, because if that were true, part of the
שליחות shlichus was to spend the whole דינר, dinar, not just to
get a shirt worth a דינר dinar or an אתרוג, esrog, you
know, worth two פרוטה peruta that he did, but part of the
שליחות shlichus was to spend the entire amount. And in this case
therefore he could have got me even a better אתרוג, esrog, a
better shirt and therefore he's not my שליח. shaliach. But now you
understand that they're only arguing this special case. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara goes
on. הכי נמי מסתברא, Hachi nami mistabra, that actually makes sense דקתני,
de-katani, we have a ברייתא braisa that says מודה רבי יהודה בקיטנית
ששניהם מעלו. Modeh Rabbi Yehuda be-kitnis she-sheneihem ma'alu. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
would agree that when it comes to קיטנית, kitnis, which is you
know legumes, that and he got you only half, that they were
both
מועל. mo-el. Why? שהקיטנית בפרוטה וקיטנית בדינר. She-ha-kitnis be-peruta ve-kitnis be-dinar. Cause
קיטנית kitnis goes for a פרוטה peruta and it goes for a
דינר dinar and therefore he agrees. Now why does that make sense?
So the גמרא's Gemara going to have a discussion the next line,
but I'll tell you, actually it makes an enormous amount of sense.
Why is קיטנית kitnis different than shirts and אתרוגים? esrogs? Can you
think? Why when it's a shirt you could buy...
yeah you could buy more for less.
Exactly. By a shirt and an אתרוג esrog it's one object so
I can say this object that cost half is a completely different
object than the one right... it's a Kmart shirt, it's not an
Armani shirt or whatever, it's a completely different object. Okay? Whereas if
we're talking about, and same with an אתרוג, esrog, small, big, it's
completely different. If we're talking about however a what do you call
it
קיטנית, kitnis, let's say legumes, apples, so if you only spent half
of my money on the apples, so I can't say oh these
were completely different. You didn't do everything that I wanted, but you
did half of what I wanted. I wanted two pounds of apples,
you brought home one pound of apples. You can't say like you
didn't do at all what I wanted, at least I have a
pound, right? So there as and also it's different from the land
case. By the land half of an acre is not is not
half of a whole acre. Right? A whole acre, you know, I
can do things with and I can't do half of them on
a half acre. But half of a bushel of apples and half
of a pound of קיטנית kitnis is half of what I asked
you to do. Okay, so that actually makes an enormous amount of
sense.
As long as a pound would just be double the price, I
mean let's say, right, I understand.
Okay, that's how I would interpret it, but let's take a look
the גמרא Gemara now sort of plays with this a little bit
and it's a little hard to understand what the answer of the
גמרא Gemara is. היכי דמי, Heichi dami, now what's the case says
the גמרא? Gemara? Does the גמרא Gemara think that the whole point
is according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is not just that it
was a different object than that but that you cheated me out
of a bargain? That's how the גמרא Gemara understands רבי יהודה. Rabbi
Yehuda. So then if that's the whole issue, not a different object
but you cheated me out of a bargain, then that's also true
by anything, by קיטנית kitnis as well. אי דאתרא דזבני בשומא, Ei
de-asra de-zavni be-shuma, if it's a place where they sort of estimate
oh looks like it's a pound or whatever, you know, if that's
true then גבי קיטנית נמי, gabi kitnis nami, so by same argument
should be by קיטנית kitnis if they're a type of places that
estimate and bargain or whatever if they gave you a bargain by
half they would have given you a bigger bargain, you know, twice
the amount you would have saved by getting the full amount. אי
יהבת סלע מוזלי טפי, Ei yahavta sela mozli tefei, if you would
have given the full סלע sela you would have saved even more
money. True then גבי כיתנא נמי, gabei kitnas nami, so by what
same argument should be by כיתנא? kitnas? If there are type of
places that estimate and bargain or whatever, if they gave you a
bargain by half, they would have given you a bigger bargain, you
know, twice the amount you would have saved by getting the full
amount. דאי יהיב סלע מוזלי ליה טפי, de-yeiv sela movzi leh tfei,
if you would have given the full סלע, sela, you would have
you would have saved even more money. So if the whole point
that רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda is saying is, "Hey, you could have
got a better bargain," so why does it matter if it's about
a shirt or if it's about כיתנא? kitnas? So the גמרא Gemara
says, אמר רב פפא Amar Rav Papa בדווקא. bedavka. The whole point
that רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda saying is, "Hey, you could have got
a better bargain," so why doesn't matter if it's about a shirt
or if it's about כיתנא? kitnas? So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר
רב פפא Amar Rav Papa בדוכתא דמזבני בקני, beduchta de-mizvni bekanei, at
the place where they sell by measure. קני קני, kanei kanei, so
בפרוטה. beproota. תני
קני... tani kanei... probably an extra קני kanei here. Every you know,
every small measure, every whatever, every grain is a פרוטה. proota. דהתם
פסיקא מילתיה, dehasam psika milsaiya, there it's exact. Okay, but if so
what's it saying? Is it saying that, oh, in the case of
כיתנית kitnis there will never be bargains? So this scenario never comes
up? Then it's pretty funny to say רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda is
מודה, modeh, right, if what we're basically saying is is that there
just won't sort of like be those scenarios. But that seems to
me to be what the גמרא Gemara is saying. It's saying this
is our proof that the only debate of רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda
and the חכמים Chachamim is is in a case of a bargain
and not a case when he just spent half the money. Because
if it was just that he spent half the money, you could
have that scenario by כיתנית kitnis as well. But if the scenario
if the argument is only in cases where there are bargains, well,
if they sell these things exactly by the gram and exactly by
the measure, there are never bargains by this. And therefore that would
be a case they would agree. So that's how the גמרא Gemara
tells us whatever, a slightly different way, but anyway it's a little
the answer is a little complicated but I think that's the best
way of understanding it here. So according to the גמרא Gemara then,
the question is if you do half and you of of something
are you still a שליח? shliach? The simple sense in the משנה
Mishna is that they debate that. Whereas the גמרא Gemara says no,
actually you're not a שליח shliach if you only did halfway, they
would all agree. The question here is you did the full amount
but you didn't you didn't get the most out of the bargain.
You didn't get it for the for the full amount of money
you were given. You got the full object but you didn't spend
the full amount of money, does that also challenge the idea of
שליחות? shlichus? And here it says that and that's could be when
the argument could be, "Hey, I could have gotten a bargain," so
obviously in a case where there were no bargains to be had,
then רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda would say then you have nothing you
could claim. Okay, but again as I said I think the difference
between the shirt and the אתרוג esrog and the land on the
one hand and the כיתנית kitnis on the other is quite clear
because those are fundamentally different objects as opposed to the כיתנית kitnis
which is just more or less. Last משנה. Mishna. Okay. המפקיד מעות
אצל שולחני. Hamaphkid ma'os etzel shulchani.
You go ahead and again all of these cases realize that all
of these cases the assumption is, right, you don't do מעילה, meilah,
your taking is not מעילה, meilah, you have to take it out
of your control or the חנווני chanvani takes it out of his
control if it was given to him and so on. So again
this sort of says that obviously that you don't need the concept
of גזבר. gizbar. Anybody that has a right to be handling it,
it's not מעילה meilah taking until they take it out of their
control. So you go ahead and you have this money that is
either you're the גזבר gizbar if you want to say that or
whatever, you have money of הקדש hekdesh in your house, and you
give it
to a שולחני. shulchani. A שולחני shulchani is a money changer. Okay,
now obviously if
you're giving if you give a purse full of coins to a
money changer, there's often an assumption that I can use those coins
if I needed to change money and I'll just reimburse you for
how much I I took. Okay. אם בצרור, Im bitzrur, if however
it was in a bundle that was bound up, knotted up, לא
ישתמש בהן, lo yishtamesh bahen, then the general rule is that a
money changer who is given money to watch that's in a bound
up pouch is not allowed to use it. לפיכך, Lephichach, therefore, אם
הוציא, im hotzi, if he used it, now he thinks it belongs
to you, you gave it to him, it really is הקדש, hekdesh,
but either way because it was bound up he wasn't allowed to
use it. So now if he does use it he's using it
in, you know, in violation, meaning he's not he's not using it
without permission, without right to be using it, and therefore אם הוציא
מעל, im hotzi ma'al, as soon as he not just takes it
again notice, but as soon as he spends it like he gives
it in change to somebody else, that's his מעילה. meilah. Okay, so
you got the scenario? He had no right to be doing it
and therefore if he spends it it's his מעילה, meilah, he's acting
on his own. It's sort of like he's not a שליח, shliach,
he's acting on his own. Okay. אם מותרים, Im mutarim, if however
they are not bound, not same word as permissible, meaning אסור asur
literally means bound and מותר mutar means unbound. So if anyway if
they are if they are not bound up, ישתמש בהן, yishtamesh bahen,
he fundamentally you know he implicitly has a right to use it
if it weren't הקדש's hekdesh money. ולפיכך אם הוציא לא מעל, Ulephichach
im hotzi lo ma'al, if he spent it he did not but
somebody
else did, somebody might have.
Who was מועל? mo'el? So was the בעל הבית ba'al habayis מועל?
mo'el? Because if I'm giving it to him I know he can
use it therefore his using it is seen as an extension of
me and I'm מועל, mo'el, possibly, that's what I think the מפרשי
התוספות mefarshei Tosafos here says. But the רמב"ם Rambam says nobody is
מועל. mo'el.
Because or not even the person who has the money?
Well, the person who gets it in the end will be מועל
mo'el when he spends it. Okay.
Is that according to everybody or
according to the רמב"ם?
Rambam? According to the רמב"ם. Rambam. The רמב"ם Rambam says I'm not
מועל mo'el as the בעל הבית ba'al habayis because I never told
him to spend it, he was still acting on his own. Okay,
so therefore he maybe with permission but it still wasn't on my
behalf. So I'm not מועל, mo'el, he's not מועל mo'el because you
know because he's acting now again the question is why is he?
Is not מועל, moel, even though he's acting, you know, with permission,
he still
took הקדש's hekdesh money and gave it to somebody else, you know.
So again, that's that's sort of like a funny thing there about
that that somehow because he thinks that he's operate—he has a license
to do it, it makes it different than just sort of ignorance.
So but again, it's a little bit funny. You would have thought
that the very spending, even even if he has a license to
do it—I mean, in the normal case, I have money around in
my house, but the difference is if I have money around in
my house that's הקדש, hekdesh, it's just my own נארישקייט narrishkeit that
I think I have the right to do it. Whereas here, he
actually—but I give him money, it's implicit, unbound, it's implicitly telling him,
"You have a license to use it." So it's like he has
permission, not just that he thinks—he actually has implicit permission from me.
So therefore, he cannot be identified as having done something wrong, and
it's only the person who actually use it.
And this is again, this is the permission meaning he has to
do it, you know what I mean? It's like you're telling him
to do it. That's right.
I I get it. That's right, explained it.
Alright, the בעל הבית balabus did not realize that it's הקדש hekdesh
when he uses this money. Yes, correct. He doesn't, correct. Exactly.
Okay, so that's okay, so that's the case. But the חנווני chanvani
is מועל moel because even though he gave it out, here it's
different somehow because he implicitly has
permission. The—I'm sorry—the שולחני shulchani and the בעל הבית balabus is a
debate, but the רמב"ם Rambam says the בעל הבית balabus is not
מועל. moel. איתיב הבעל הבית, eitav habalabus, now let's say the money
was given not to a money changer, but to, you know, a
normal person, a homeowner, a normal person. בין כך ובין כך לא
ישתמש בהן. bein kach u'bein kach lo ishtamesh ben. If I just
give it to a normal—my friend to watch money for me, even
if it's not tied up and bound up, there's no assumption that
he's allowed to use
it.
And therefore, the בעל הבית, balabus, right?
Yeah. So so therefore, this—yeah, these issues about when you have a
right to use things that are under that are given to you
for safekeeping. So since he doesn't have a right to use it
regardless of the
scenario, לפיכך אם הוציא מעל. lefichach im hotzi maal. Okay, therefore if
he spends it, he's totally acting on his own without permission, and
as soon as he goes ahead and spends that money, he's מועל,
moel, not me. Now, what about החנווני? hachanvani? What about the storekeeper,
right? If I give money to a storekeeper for safekeeping, he's not
like a money changer that he's constantly using the funds, but you
know, storekeepers also sometimes need change. So is there an implicit permission
for a storekeeper to use my money if it's not bound up?
החנווני כבעל הבית דברי רבי מאיר. hachanvani k’balabus divrei rabbi meir. So
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says no, he's like a homeowner, there's no
permission for a storekeeper even if it's not
bound. רבי יהודה אומר כשולחני. Rabbi Yehuda omer k’shulchani. He's like a
money changer and there is implicit permission. Okay, so what the new
thing we learned here is again, number one, all these cases where
it seems pretty clear, even if somebody isn't the גזבר, gizbar, there's
no מעילה meila until the money's actually gone out to a third
party, right? Number one. Number two, that that the interesting approach of
the רמב"ם Rambam that you could have a middle case where he
has implicit permission but he's not my שליח, shaliach, and therefore since
he's not—I didn't tell him to do it, there's no מעילה. meila.
And the third point, maybe the prime point is the which is
the biggest חידוש chiddush I would say is that the שולחני shulchani
is not מועל moel even though he is taking הקדש's hekdesh money
and spending it. The fact that he has—seems to believe he has
permission or he does have permission from the בעל הבית, balabus, although
it's not genuine permission because—but the fact that he was given implicit
permission is enough to say that he is not doing an act
of מעילה. meila. Isn't there—it's not somehow it's not an act of
violation. As before we said that even you're an אונס, oness, you
could still be מועל, moel, but here it's more than אונס, oness,
here it is some type of implicit permission. Okay, anyway, so yeah,
I'm not sure that really works, and that's because, you know, you
know what it doesn't work with? It doesn't work with the case
when I send the שליח shaliach and I remember that the שליח
shaliach is מועל. moel. Because if I send the שליח, shaliach, if
he violates, he's not acting with permission. But if I send him
and I remember, then he when he's acting is still acting on
my orders. And if we say even there the שליח shaliach is
מועל, moel, it's hard to imagine why the שליח shaliach is מועל
moel in that case when I remember, and here the חנווני chanvani
isn't מועל. moel.
Particularly, particularly given that the משנה mishna actually says what the householder
is supposed to do, yeah, to to fix it, and if he
doesn't, yeah, so
what's the point?
Well, it
just reinforces your point
that why—my question is: somebody acting with permission, can they ever be
מועל? moel? And here it sounds like no, the חנווני, chanvani, but
the שליח shaliach when the בעל הבית balabus remembers is מועל, moel,
okay, right. So okay, so anyway, I don't get it exactly. Let's
keep on going. נפל פרוטה של הקדש בתוך כיסו. nafal pruta shel
hekdesh betoch kiso. Let's say you accidentally dropped a הקדש hekdesh פרוטה
pruta in your purse.
You're the בעל הבית.
balabus. Yes, we're away from בעל הבית balabus and חנווני, chanvani, totally
new scenario. You dropped a הקדש hekdesh coin in your purse.
Where were we? נפל פרוטה pruta של הקדש hekdesh, בתוך כיסו—או שאמר
פרוטה pruta. בכיסי הקדש, or you said a פרוטה in my purse
is הקדש, and you didn't say which פרוטה. כיוון שהוציא את הראשונה
מעל דברי רבי עקיבא. kivan she-hotzi es harishona maal divrei rabbi akiva.
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says as soon as you take out the
first... first one, that's the הקדש *Hekdesh* one in your מעל *maal*.
וחכמים אומרים *ve-Chachamim omrim* עד שיוציא את כל הכיס *ad sheyotzi et
kol hakis*, only after you spent all the money. Now the חכמים
*Chachamim* of course make sense. Until you spent all the money, you
don't know that you spent the הקדש *Hekdesh* coin. What's רבי עקיבא'ס
*Rabbi Akiva's* position? Well, if it was just the case I said
one coin in my purse is הקדש *Hekdesh* and I sanctified it,
you could say what I mean to say is the first one
I take out. Okay, we can somehow interpret it that way, that's
fine. But if I drop a coin in my purse, how could
you say the first one I'm מועל *moel*? It's a ספק *safek*,
which is which? How can you say I'm מועל *moel* with the
first one, right? Pretty good question. So the תוספתא *Tosefta*, תוספות *Tosafos*
quotes the תוספתא *Tosefta*, the תוספתא *Tosefta* says רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*
says what happens when you spend the first one? Not exactly מועל
*moel*, but you bring an אשם תלוי *asham taluy* for מעילה *me'ilah*.
If you remember back to כריתות *Kerisos*, רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* said
that is can you bring an אשם תלוי *asham taluy* for מעילה
*me'ilah*, because מעילה *me'ilah* is itself an אשם *asham*. רבי עקיבא *Rabbi
Akiva* said yes and the חכמים *Chachamim* said no. So according to
the תוספתא *Tosefta*, he doesn't really mean מועל *moel* in the case
when it got mixed up, he means you were ספק *safek* מועל
*moel* and therefore you're going to bring an אשם תלוי *asham taluy*.
And then after you spend all the coins, then you would bring
of course an אשם ודאי *asham vadai* for מעילה *me'ilah*. So that's
how the תוספתא *Tosefta* explains רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*, without that it
doesn't make any sense. Now I do want to say that תוספות
*Tosafos* also asks another question, which is a
fascinating question. תוספות *Tosafos* says why isn't the coin that you drop
in the purse בטל ברוב *batel berov*? If you have multiple coins,
why don't we just apply the principle of ביטול *bitul*? And he
says don't tell me principles like דבר שיש לו מתירין *davar sheyesh
lo matirin* or this or that, because that's all דרבנן *De-Rabbanan* and
here it's a דאורייתא *De-Oraisa* question of
מעילה *me'ilah*. So one answer
תוספות *Tosafos* says is maybe there were just two coins, so it's
just mixed up with not a lot of coins, but I mean
there's just one coin and this coin. The other answer תוספות *Tosafos*
says is you know what, maybe דאורייתא *De-Oraisa* also the idea like
a coin maybe is a דבר חשוב *davar chashuv* and not בטל
*batel*, maybe that's a דאורייתא *De-Oraisa* reason why it's not בטל *batel*.
And תוספות *Tosafos* gives answers like that. But Charlie says it doesn't
make sense and I also intuitively agree with Charlie. Why do you
think it doesn't make sense, Charlie?
Well, an example of כשרות *kashrut* is so we can't cook meat
and milk mixtures together, but there are times if we drop some
milk into the meat it will be בטל *batel*.
Oh so that does make sense, the question, you agree with the
question of תוספות *Tosafos*, why isn't it בטל *batel*? Yeah, yeah. So
תוספות *Tosafos* says either there's only one coin or maybe it's important,
a coin and even דאורייתא *De-Oraisa* not בטל *batel*. But I would
tell you here's a question, let me give you another scenario. I
go ahead and
Michael has 100 dollars and he accidentally
drops it into a box of my dollar bills or whatever and
I say, oh well you know what Michael, too bad, it was
בטל ברוב *batel berov*. I don't know exactly which dollar is yours,
it's בטל ברוב *batel berov*, so they're all mine. So obviously right
we don't say בטל *batel*, we say בטל *batel* when it's about
status, we don't say בטל *batel* when it's about ownership, right? You
still own it and therefore it doesn't stop being yours even though
you can't find it. So the interesting question is what would we
say by הקדש *Hekdesh* here? Right? Because on the one hand it's
about status, so if we're just looking at it as an איסור
*issur*, we should say בטל ברוב *batel berov*. But on the other
hand, it's הקדש'ס *Hekdesh's* money. You don't say, oh I'm sorry, I
can't give you your money back, it's בטל *batel*.
And you certainly pull out a some coin and give it back
to הקדש *Hekdesh*. Right. Whether they sample the soup, you can't get
the milk back.
Right. Well, that's, yes, that's another issue about יבש ביבש *yavesh be-yavesh*
and לח בלח *lach be-lach*, but the more important point here is
that there's a question of ownership. You don't say ביטול *bitul* by
that, you say ביטול *bitul* by status. Anyway, let's keep on going.
So, wait, how do we explain it?
That's how I would explain why there's no ביטול *bitul*. Boom. Okay.
ומודה רבי עקיבא לחכמים *u-modeh Rabbi Akiva le-Chachamim* באומר פרוטה מן הכיס
זה הקדש *be-omer pruta min hakis zeh Hekdesh*, but רבי עקיבא *Rabbi
Akiva* agrees with the חכמים *Chachamim* that if you don't say פרוטה
בכיס זה הקדש *pruta be-kis zeh Hekdesh*, but you say פרוטה מן
כיס זה הקדש *pruta min kis zeh Hekdesh*, from this purse, not
in this purse, but from, שמוציא והולך עד שיוציא את כל הכיס
*she-motzi ve-holekh ad she-yotzi et kol ha-kis*, that then it's only the
last coin. That somehow if you say a פרוטה *pruta* in, you
mean the first one, if you say a פרוטה *pruta* from, you
mean the last one. The גמרא *Gemara* doesn't exactly understand the difference,
so let's take a look at the גמרא *Gemara*. גמרא *Gemara* says
like this, כי אתא רב דימי אמר ריש לקיש *ki ata Rav
Dimi amar Reish Lakish*, רמי ליה רישא אסיפא *rami lei reisha a-seifa*
דרבי יוחנן *de-Rabbi Yochanan*. ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* challenged רבי יוחנן *Rabbi
Yochanan*. מאי שנא רישא ומאי שנא סיפא *mai shna reisha u-mai shna
seifa*? What difference does it make whether you say בכיס *be-kis* or
מן כיס *min kis*? It's all the same. So אמר ליה *amar
lei*, סיפא באומר לא יפטר כיס זה מן ההקדש *seifa be-omer lo
yiftar kis zeh min ha-Hekdesh*. So he completely, he says no, you
don't just say מן כיס זה *min kis zeh*, then it would
be more or less the same. He says let it be not
spend this, this purse will not be free from הקדש *Hekdesh*, which
means, which means that there will be some הקדש *Hekdesh* left in
this purse, which means the last coin. But you say a very,
a very specific and strange terminology. If you just said the language
of the משנה *Mishna*, it's true, it would mean the first coin
for רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*. Okay. כי אתא רבין *ki ata Ravin*,
when רבין *Ravin* came from ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*, אמר *amar*, כיסין
אשברם *kisin ashvaram* רמי ליה *rami lei*. Everybody had different versions about
what this discussion of ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* and רבי יוחנן *Rabbi
Yochanan* was about. He says that they were... from our case about
the money purses to a case about oxen. What’s that? דתנן *Detnan*,
we taught in the משנה *Mishna*, האומר אחד משורי הקדש *ha'omer echad
mishurai hekdesh*, one of my oxen is הקדש *hekdesh*. היו לו שנים
*Hayu lo shenayim*, if you have two, הגדול שבהן הקדש *hagadol shebahen
hekdesh*, the bigger one is הקדש *hekdesh*. So it says fine, yeah,
exactly, we assume you want to give the big one. So we
said here if you said one coin in my purse, why are
we saying, why do we say it’s the first one or it’s
the last one? Why don’t we say it’s like the best one,
the nicest one? Why is this different? So אמר ליה *amar lei*,
סיפא *seifa*, so he says, you know what, maybe. סיפא באומר לא
יפטר כיס זה מן ההקדש *Seifa be’omer lo yipater kis zeh min
hahekdesh*. The end of the משנה *Mishna* is a case where you
said the same point explicitly: it won’t be exempt from הקדש *hekdesh*,
which means the very last one. So
and presumably in the first case, not exactly clear why in the
first case it means any one, but at least in the last
case you say, yeah, go ahead.
Wait, so in the case let’s say I have my wallet full
of quarters and nickels and dimes, and I say one of these
is הקדש *hekdesh*, then I’m not מועל *mo’el* even according to רבי
עקיבא *Rebbe Akiva* if I spend all my dimes and all my
nickels. I’m only מועל *mo’el* once I’ve spent all the quarters? Well,
that’s the question.
So תוספות *Tosafot* says somehow we could accept that the language of
פרוטה בכיס זה *pruta bekis zeh* does somehow doesn’t mean the best,
but means, means, means the first. Okay, the רישא *reisha* we could
accept. Maybe the first is a concept of like the best. But
how do you get to a concept of not the best, not
the first, but the last? That’s the question. So the גמרא *Gemara*
gives the same answer, אמר ליה *amar lei*, סיפא
באומר לא יפטר כיס זה מן
ההקדש *seifa be’omer lo yipater kis zeh min hahekdesh*, you did stipulate,
you were explicit. So basically רבי עקיבא *Rebbe Akiva* in other times
would not say the last one. Maybe we would say it’s the
more expensive one, right? Or maybe the first. It’s a little unclear
which one we would prefer. Okay, let’s take a look. רב פפא
*Rav Pappa* אמר *amar* another case, קיסני אלוגין רמי ליה *kisanei alugin
rami
lei*. He asks from the question from our case of purses to
the case about the like whatever the what do they call it
canteens or whatever, the bottles of wine. דתנן *Detnan*, הלוקח יין מבין
הכותים *halokeach yayin mibein hakutim*, somebody bought wine from the Samaritans, so
he has to assume that תרומות ומעשרות *terumot uma’asrot* weren’t taken. It’s
even worse than דמאי *demai*, you have to assume even תרומה *teruma*
wasn’t taken. And you’re in a rush and you can’t exactly, it’s
ערב שבת *erev Shabbat* or whatever it is and you can’t do
all the הפרשה *hafrasha* right now. So אומר *omer*, שני לוגין שאני
עתיד להפריש *shnei lugin she’ani atid lehafrish*, the two units that eventually
I will take, maybe let’s say after שבת *Shabbat*, הרי הן תרומה
*harei hen teruma*, they’ll be תרומה *teruma*. עשרה מעשר ראשון *asara ma’aser
rishon*, then I’m going to take ten more that’ll be the first
tithe. תשעה מעשר שני *tisha ma’aser sheni*, then I’m left with ninety,
right? If you imagine you started with a hundred and two units,
two is תרומה *teruma*, then ten is ten percent, then we’re left
with ninety, then nine is the next ten percent. That’s the second
tithe. ומחל *umechal*, which probably means you transfer the קדושה *kedusha* of
the מעשר שני *ma’aser sheni* onto a coin, all of this you
could do immediately. ושותה מיד *veshoteh miyad*, and you can drink even
though you haven’t taken תרומות ומעשרות *terumot uma’asrot*, you can say the
stuff at the end that I’ll take will be the תרומות ומעשרות
*terumot uma’asrot* now. This is a ברירה *breira* case. I’m not right
now not taking it and not designating it, but the stuff I
will make sure to leave stuff over and the stuff I leave
over, that’ll be the תרומות ומעשרות *terumot uma’asrot*. So רבי מאיר *Rebbe
Meir* says that works, יש ברירה *yesh breira*. רבי יהודה ורבי יוסי
ורבי שמעון אוסרין *Rebbe Yehuda veRebbe Yossi veRebbe Shimon osrin*. Oh, all
these three, רבי יהודה ורבי יוסי ורבי שמעון *Rebbe Yehuda veRebbe Yossi
veRebbe Shimon*, all say it’s forbidden. They don’t hold of ברירה *breira*.
Okay, now so why is this a question? So תוספות *Tosafot* says
the question is, let me just double check תוספות *Tosafot* again.
Right, he says like this. He says that even according to the
opinion, one minute. According to רבי מאיר *Rebbe Meir*, ah, he says
like this, here’s how תוספות *Tosafot* understands the question. תוספות *Tosafot* says
according to רבי מאיר *Rebbe Meir*, in order to get the last
stuff to be תרומה ומעשר *teruma uma’aser*, you have to explicitly stipulate
that it’s תרומה ומעשר *teruma uma’aser*. If that’s true, he says, then
how does that work with רבי עקיבא *Rebbe Akiva*? We’re assuming it
could work with רבי עקיבא *Rebbe Akiva*. רבי עקיבא *Rebbe Akiva* says
that you don’t have to stipulate, that if you just said פרוטה
בכיס זה הקדש *pruta bekis zeh hekdesh*, you know, for whatever reason
in the סיפא *seifa* he seems to say that that the last
one would be הקדש *hekdesh*, even if you didn’t stipulate. But here
if you wanted the last stuff to work you have to stipulate.
How does that work? So the גמרא *Gemara* gives the same answer,
אמר ליה *amar lei*, סיפא דמתניתין באומר לא יפטר כיס זה מן
ההקדש *seifa dematnitin be’omer lo yipater kis zeh min hahekdesh*, you did
stipulate, you were explicit. So basically רבי עקיבא *Rebbe Akiva* in other
times would not say the last one. You know, the חכמים *Chachamim*
say it’s always like a ספק *safek* and you have to spend
all the money until you do it ודאי *vadai*. רבי עקיבא *Rebbe
Akiva* says normally it’s the first one, but sometimes it’s the last
one. And the question is when is it the last one? Why,
when should we say
that? So the גמרא *Gemara*’s basically answer is you were very explicit
and clear and your language meant it was the last one. הדרן
עלך שליח שעשה שליחותו וסליקא לה מסכת מעילה *Hadran alach Shaliach She’asa
Shlichuto uslika lah Masechet Me’ila*. That is it for מעילה *Me’ila*. יישר
כח *Yashar koach* everybody.